Wendell Minor Papers
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Wendell Minor Papers.
undated, circa 1970-2004
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Minor, Wendell.
8.25 linear feet.
The Wendell Minor Papers include incomplete sets of manuscripts, dummies, sketches, drawings, illustrations, and proofs associated with fifteen books illustrated by Wendell Minor. The collection also contains greeting cards and posters illustrated by Minor.
MSS20040075
Biography
Wendell Minor was born 17 March 1944 in Aurora, Illinois, the son of Gordon and Marjorie (Sebby) Minor. He graduated from Ringling School of Art and Design in 1966. An artist and illustrator, Minor has been a member of the faculty of the School of Visual Arts (New York) from 1975 until 1986 and a freelance author/illustrator since 1970. He is also a member of advisory council, Connecticut Center for the Book (Hartford, CT) and a lecturer to college and universities throughout the United States. Minor has exhibited his work at the New York Art Directors Club (New York, 1992), Mystic Maritime Gallery (Mystic, CT, 1992-1995), Lyman Allyn Art Museum (New London, CT), Columbus Museum of Art (Columbus, OH), Art Institute of Chicago, Boston Public Library, The Bruce Museum (Greenwich, CT), Muskegon Museum of Art (Muskegon, MI) and Silo Gallery (New Milford, CT). Minor's work is also included in the permanent collections of Illinois State Museum, Mattatuck Museum, Arizona Historical Society, NASA, Library of Congress, Museum of American Illustration, U.S. Coast Guard Academy, the Norman Rockwell Museum, and the Mazza Collection at Findlay University.
The more notable of the many honors and awards Minor has received for his work include the following:
Abe Lincoln Remembers--Notable Children’s Trade Books in the Field of Social Studies (2001).
Everglades--Notable Book designation, Smithsonian (1995); and Silver Honor award, Parents Choice Foundation, and named Notable Children's Trade Book in the Field of Social Studies (1996).
Fire Storm--Best Book Award-Oppenheim Toy Portfolio (2004).
Grand Canyon--Smithsonian's Notable Books for Children award (1998); Notable Children's Trade Book in the Field of Social Studies; Smithsonian’s Notable Books for Children (1998).
Grassroots--Certificate of Merit, Bookbuilders West Book Show (1998).
Heartland--1989 Notable Children's Trade Books in Social Studies, National Council for the Social Studies/Children's Book Council (1990); Merit award, New York Art Directors Club (1993); National Council of Teachers of English 1990 Notable Trade Books in the Language Arts (1991); International Reading Association/Children’s Book Council Favorite Paperbacks for 1994 (1994); 1989 John Burroughs List of Nature Books For Young Readers (1990); ALA Booklist Children’s Editors’ Choices for 1989 (1989).
Into the Woods: John James Audubon Lives His Dream--NSTA/CBC Outstanding Science Trade Books for Children (1992); Connecticut Center For the Book - Best Illustrated Children’s Picture Book (2004)
A Lucky Thing--A Child Magazine Best Book of the Year.
Mojave--1988 Notable Children's Trade Books in Social Studies, National Council for the Social Studies/Children's Book Council (1989); Book List 1988 Childrens’ Editors Choices (1989); International Reading Association 1989 Teachers’ Choices (1989); International Reading Association/Children’s Book Council Favorite Paperbacks for 1994 (1994); 1988 John Burroughs List of Nature Books For Young Readers (1989); ALA Booklist Children’s Choices for 1988 (1988).
Rachel: The Story of Rachel Carson--Parents’ Choice Award (2003); John Burroughs List of Nature Books For Young Readers (one of six books selected, 2003); NSTA/CBC Outstanding Science Trade Books for Children 1992 (2003).
Red Fox Running--Award of Excellence, Communication Arts (1993).
The Seashore Book--1992 Notable Children's Trade Books in Social Studies, National Council for the Social Studies/Children's Book Council (1993); John and Patricia Beatty Award, California Library Association (1992); and Teachers' Choice designation, International Reading Association (1992); 1992 Outstanding Science Trade Books for Children, National Science Teachers Association/Children's Book Council (1993).
Sierra--1991 Notable Children's Trade Books in Social Studies, National Council for the Social Studies/Children's Book Council (1992); 1991 Outstanding Science Trade Books for Children, National Science Teachers Association/Children's Book Council (1992); IRA Teachers’ Choice (1992); 1991 John Burroughs List of Nature Books For Young Readers (1992).
Snow Bear--NCTE Notable Children’s Books in the English Language Arts (National Council of Teachers of English, 2000).
Published Works, Self-Illustrated:
(With wife, Florence Minor) Art for the Written Word: Twenty-five Years of Book Cover Art, Harcourt, 1995.
Grand Canyon: Exploring a Natural Wonder, Blue Sky Press, 1998.
Pumpkin Heads!, Blue Sky Press, 2000.
Illustrator:
Jane Goodsell, Eleanor Roosevelt, Crowell, 1970.
Diane Siebert, Mojave, Crowell, 1988.
Diane Siebert, Heartland, Crowell, 1989.
Diane Siebert, Sierra, HarperCollins, 1991.
Charlotte Zolotow, The Seashore Book, HarperCollins, 1992.
Jean Craighead George, The Moon of the Owls, HarperCollins, 1993.
Eve Bunting, Red Fox Running, Clarion, 1993.
Jean Craighead George, Julie, HarperCollins, 1994.
Jean Craighead George, Everglades, HarperCollins, 1995.
Ann Turner, Shaker Hearts, HarperCollins, 1997.
Jean Craighead George, Arctic Son, Hyperion, 1997.
Jean Craighead George, Julie's Wolf Pack, HarperCollins, 1997.
Carl Sandburg, Grassroots, Browndeer Press, 1998.
Jean Craighead George, Morning, Noon, and Night, HarperCollins, 1999.
Jean Craighead George, Snow Bear, Hyperion, 1999.
Pat Brisson, Sky Memories, Delacorte, 1999.
Alice Schertle, A Lucky Thing, Harcourt, 1999.
Jack London, The Call of the Wild, Atheneum, 1999.
A. Turner, Abe Lincoln Remembers, HarperCollins, 2001.
Eve Bunting, We Were There: A Nativity Story, Clarion, 2001.
Jean Craighead George, Lonesome George, HarperCollins, 2001.
Tony Johnston, Cat, What Is That?, HarperCollins, 2001.
Jack Schaefer, Shane, Houghton Mifflin, 2001.
Jean Craighead George, Cliff Hanger, HarperCollins, 2002.
Stephen Crane, The Red Badge of Courage, Scribners Classics, 2002.
Jean Craighead George, Fire Storm, Katherine Tegen Books, 2003.
Robert Burleigh, Into the Woods: John James Audubon Lives His Dream, Atheneum, 2003.
Amy Ehrlich, Rachel: The Story of Rachel Carson, Harcourt, 2003.
Katherine Lee Bates, America the Beautiful, Putnam, 2003.
Michael Dennis Browne, Giver Her the River: A Father's Wish for His Daughter, Atheneum, 2004.
Jean Craighead George, Snowboard Twist, Katherine Tegen Books, 2004.
Buzz Aldrin, Reaching for the Moon, HarperCollins, 2005.
Florence Minor, Christmas Tree!, HarperCollins, 2005.
Scope and Content
The Wendell Minor Papers include incomplete sets of manuscripts, dummies, sketches, drawings, illustrations, and proofs associated with fifteen books illustrated by Wendell Minor. The collection also contains greeting cards and posters illustrated by Minor.
Arrangement
Series I: Books ( undated, 1970-2004 ) contains manuscripts, dummies, and artwork associated with several of the titles listed above.
Series II: Other Illustrations ( undated, 1989-2004 ) includes greetings cards and posters of Minor's illstrations.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of children's literature and related artwork. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and relocated as indicated:
Everglades (contact sheets) Photograph collection.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Minor, Wendell.
Subjects:
Children's literature, American 20th century.; Children's literature--Illustrations.; Authors, American 20th century.
Document Types:
Publications.; Artwork.; Illustrations.; Manuscripts.; Galley proofs.; Photocopies.; Notes.; Sketches.; Drawings.; Posters.; Works of art.
Occupations:
Authors, American.; Illustrators, American.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The materials were deposited by Mr. Minor in 2004.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Books, undated, 1970-2004
  - Arctic Son, 1997
    - Sketches (original), 1996 September (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Eleanor Roosevelt, 1970
    - Original illustration (watercolor), circa 1970 (Box 2:, Folder 2)
  - Everglades, 1995
    - Contact sheets, undated
    - Sketches (original), undated (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Giver Her the River, 2004
    - Proof, 2003 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Grand Canyon, 1998
    - Dummy reproduction, undated (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - Heartland, 1989
    - Manuscript, undated (Box 1:, Folder 7)
    - Dummy, 1989 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
    - Proofs, undated (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - Into the Woods, 2003
    - Proofs (2 sets), undated (Box 1:, Folder 10)
  - Julie, 1994
    - Sketches (original), undated (Box 2:, Folder 11)
  - Mojave, 1988
    - Manuscript, undated (Box 1:, Folder 12)
    - sketches (originals), undated (Box 1:, Folder 13)
    - Sketches (copies), undated (Box 1:, Folder 14)
    - Proofs, undated (Box 1:, Folder 15)
    - Uncut proof, undated (Box OS:, Folder 16)
    - Jacket proof, undated (Box 1:, Folder 17)
  - Moon of the Owls, 1993
    - Dummy, undated (Box 1:, Folder 20)
    - Sketches (originals), undated (Box 1:, Folder 21)
    - Sketches (copies), undated (Box 1:, Folder 22)
    - Text proof, undated (Box 1:, Folder 23)
    - First proofs, undated (Box 1:, Folder 24)
    - Second proofs, undated (Box 1:, Folder 25)
  - Morning, Noon and Night, 1999
    - Original sketches, undated (Box 1:, Folder 26)
    - Original sketches, undated (Box 2:, Folder 27)
  - Shane, 2001
    - Original illustration (mounted), 2001 (Box 2:, Folder 28)
  - Sierra, 1991
    - Original drawings and copies, undated (Box 1:, Folder 29)
- Series II: Other Illustrations, undated, 1989-2004
  - Greeting Cards--Boxed, 1989 (Box 3:, Folder 30)
  - Greeting Cards--Loose, 1996-2004 (Box 3:, Folder 31)
  - Posters--"America the Beautiful", 2004 (Box OS:, Folder 32)